Harriet Bliss Ford Papers, 1899-1953
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Harriet Bliss Ford papers
1899-1953
Ford, Harriet Bliss, 1876-1964
MS 59
5 boxes (2 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Civic leader; editor; YWCA executive; Red Cross official; and Trustee, Smith College. The correspondence and subject files of the Ford Papers document her work with Century Magazine and her political and intellectual life during her residence in Northampton, Massachusetts. Included is material written and published by Ford for the Young Women's Christian Association (YWCA), and manuscripts of her speeches and writings. Notable correspondents include Carrie Chapman Catt; Grace Coolidge; Elizabeth Cutter Morrow; William Allen Neilson; Ada Comstock Notestein; Abby Rockefeller; William Rose Bennet; Helena Gilder; and Eleanor Roosevelt.
Harriet Chalmers Bliss was born in New York City and earned a B.L. from Smith College in 1899. She was an editorial assistant at Century Magazine, 1899-1912, and consulting editor of the Woman's Press Board, the Woman's Journal, 1927-29. She married George Burdett Ford in 1912. Ford was director of women personal in the American Red Cross Overseas, 1917-1920, and was chair of the Smith College Relief Unit, Pans Office. Ford was on the National Board of the YWCA from 1920 to 1930, and was vice president chair of the Publicity Organization. She was a member of the Committee on Cause and Cure of War from 1925 to1930. At Smith College, she was a publicity chair and trustee, 1923-36, and she was a "Trustee in Residence," 1931-36. She was on the Board of Directors of the Smith Alumnae Association and the American Association of University Women. Ford was involved in Northampton, Massachusetts city politics and the National League of Women Voters, 1950s. She was on the Northampton City Charter Committee, 1949, and the City Council, 1940s-50s. She wrote articles, poetry and plays, some of which were published, regarding various causes including women's issues and peace.
The papers include biographical materials, correspondence, memorabilia, photographs, writings, and subject files. The correspondence and subject files relate to her work with Century Magazine and her political and intellectual life during her residence in Northampton, Massachusetts. Included are plays and pageants written and published by Ford for the Young Women's Christian Association (as well as other YWCA publications), and manuscripts of her speeches and writings. There is also an unpublished biography of her husband, George B. Ford. Notable correspondents include Carrie Chapman Catt; Grace Coolidge; Elizabeth Cutter Morrow; William Allen Neilson; Ada Comstock Notestein; Abby Rockefeller; William Rose Bennet; Helena Gilder. and Eleanor Roosevelt.
This collection is organized into five series:
I. Biographical Materials
II. Writings
III. Memorabilia
IV. Correspondence
V. Subjects
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The collection is open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
History of the Collection
Materials in this collection were given to the Sophia Smith Collection by Harriet Bliss Ford and her niece.
Search Terms
Catt, Carrie Chapman, 1859-1947--Correspondence; Coolidge, Grace Goodhue, 1879-1957--Correspondence; Ford, Harriet Bliss, 1876-1964; H. de K. G. (Helena de Kay Gilder)--Correspondence; Morrow, Elizabeth, 1873-1955--Correspondence; Neilson, William Allan, 1869-1946--Correspondence; Rockefeller, Abby Aldrich--Correspondence; Century Magazine--History; National Committee on the Cause and Cure of War (U.S.); League of Women Voters of Northampton (Mass.)--History; Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A. National Board--History; Smith College--Administration--History--Sources; Northampton, (Mass.)--History--Sources; Women editors--United States--20th century--Sources; Women and peace--History--20th century--Sources
Additional Information
Related Material
There are additional papers of Harriet Bliss Ford located in the Smith College Archives.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
  - Biographical sketch (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence
    - Business, 1913-50 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Personal, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - European diary, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters of congratulation, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters of recommendation, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letters of condolence (on death of George B. Ford), 1930-31 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Speeches, 1936, 1955, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- SERIES II. WRITINGS
  - Writings
    - Published, 1922-50 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Unpublished, 1950-58, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Ford, George B.
      - Biography (unpublished manuscript), 1931 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Correspondence (re: biography), 1931 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- SERIES III. MEMORABILIA
  - Greeting cards (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 5)
- SERIES IV. CORRESPONDENCE
  - Allen, Ruth Strickland, 1909-23 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Barnard, Eunice Fuller, 1935-36 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Barrett, Halsey M., 1899 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Benet, William Rose, 1912-21 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Brown, "Dot", undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Buel, Clarence Clough, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Cather, Willa Sibert, 1909 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Coolidge, Grace, 1943, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Crowinshield, Frank, 1912-15 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Dreier, Katherine S. 1924-25 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Ellsworth, W.W., 1913, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Ford, Eleanor Burdette, 1912 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Gilder, Helena, 1910-13 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Gilder, Richard Watson, 1905-09 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Gilder, Rodman, 1909-10 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Herter, Christian, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Johnson, R.U., 1912-37 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Jones, Louis and Mary, 1947-49 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Kennedy, John F., 1957 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Lehman, Herbert H., 1936 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Melvin, Mary Armstrong, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Miscellaneous, 1909-33 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Morrow, Elizabeth Cutter, 1927-31 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Neilson, William Allen, 1929-31 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Newton, E. Swift, 1935-36, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Notestein, Ada Comstock, 1930-31 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Paine, Albert Bigelow, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Parsons, Edgarton and Alice, 1909-29 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Pearman, Mabel (Capelle), 1912 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Reston, James, 1952-53 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Rice, Alice Hegan, undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Rockefeller, Abby A., 1931, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Skinner, Belle, 1924-31 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Slater, Florence W., 1916 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Wilson, Claggett, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Unidentified (Box 3, Folder 38)
- SERIES V. SUBJECTS
  - Cause and Cure of War
    - General (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - League of Nations (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Mary A. Burnam School: Commencement, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Railroad report (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Roadside improvement (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - World's Fair: NY, 1938-39 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - YWCA
    - General (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - The New Creation (correspondence and information re: festival) (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - City of Northampton
    - City charter
      - Committee minutes and correspondence (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Revision and photocopies (Box 5, Folder 2-3)
    - City Council: unicameral election (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Map of Northampton (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Tercentenary celebration (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Northampton League of Women Voters (Box 5, Folder 7)